I can look up anything, anytime, any
place. I have information with me
everywhere. But how does that all fit
together? How how do I bring these
truths together? And how do those truths
actually speak to my life? Like, how
what do they have to say about how I
raise my children? What do they say
about how I treat other people at work?
Catholicism gives people the possibility
of doing that. And I think that that's
an exciting opportunity for Catholic AI
to engage with those questions and let
people have fun, let people challenge
the system, let people uh ask and kind
of enter into this updated version of
the Scholastic University where you'd
have the disputed questions where you'd
have the back and forth. uh it's the
opportunity to kind of bring that
reality and that harmonization of
different disciplines that existed in
the great universities of the past.
Maybe we can bring that reality to every
phone, every computer in the world. And
that's exciting.
Hello and welcome to the Catholic
Futurist podcast. My name is Benjamin
Crockett and I am your host. We look at
the world of tomorrow, the emerging
technologies and we look at those forks
and we bring in the moral and
intellectual tradition of the church.
And today is my great honor and my great
pleasure to be speaking with Father
Michael Bagot here in Rome.
>> Hi man, great to be here.
>> It is fantastic to be here with you. Um,
Father Michael and we're in our new
studio here on the day after Pope Leo
the 14th has been uh has been announced.
>> Very exciting. Yeah, we were both there
for the announcement and uh we were a
bit surprised.
>> Yeah. I know. I mean, it's just
absolutely exciting and incredible. And
um speaking of that, the exciting
incredible news is the world of AI that
keeps marching faster and faster
forward. And father, one of our big
projects here at Longbeard and with the
Catholic Futurist podcast is to look at
AI and to try to bring in those Catholic
values, those Catholic um themes and to
embed it into this new technology. But
um Father, while we're doing that,
um why is Catholic AI important? Why is
it important for the church to be
involved?
>> Well, AI is shaping practically every
dimension of life. We can look at the
workforce, education, medicine,
warfare,
relationships in the family, among
friends, practically every aspect of
life. So, we as a church, as an expert
in humanity, want to make sure we're
giving the right guidance and make sure
that these great values are informing
and shaping the design of AI systems. So
I think the Catholic AI comes primarily
in that aspect of promoting the right
values and making sure that these
different systems are welldesigned. And
we live in an age of confusion. We live
in an age sometimes of deception, of
manipulation. And so we want to make
sure that we're sharing the truth. these
systems are promoting the truth and are
reliable and that different users
>> have a certain confidence that they are
gaining the right guidance, the right
responses. We may never reach that
perfectly, but we at least can do our
best to design them to move in that
direction. And father, when you're
speaking with people who are working
actively in artificial intelligence, do
you find that a good majority of them
have values that we could align and say
that they are Catholic or are the
majority of them, you know, kind of
floating around in that secular space
and not thinking in terms of those
traditional Catholic values?
>> Well, I think that there is a deep
fundamental human desire for truth. You
know, St. Augustine a long time ago said
that all of us uh many people may
deceive but no one wants to be deceived.
So I think there is this fundamental
desire for truth and unfortunately there
are also some temptations to let that
value become a little secondary to
economic expediency to
ease of use to a notion of engagement in
which the particular user is just so
compelled to stay on the platform. We've
seen this recently with some problems in
the rather psychopantic design in major
large language model design where people
are told that they are absolute geniuses
even when they quite deliberately put in
uh rather
dumb prompts uh to test the system.
They're told that they basically are
brilliant and misunderstood and that
they need to keep going forward in their
creative expression. So there's that
temptation to flatter users, if you
will, to kind of deepen that engagement.
And that's where we start to see this
fundamental longing for truth set to the
wayside.
And father, when you when you look at,
you know, the challenges that AI poses
and also the challenges that we have in
in building, you know, AI with these
values, what do you think are the
challenges that are most worth tackling
for the church within AI?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. I think
that we need the humility to recognize
that there are a lot of complicated
questions out there, philosophical
questions, moral questions. And so there
can be a temptation sometimes to just
sort of promote a narrow political
ideology or some other narrow view. So,
we want to make sure that people who are
coming to different systems are really
getting information, getting the tools
they need to do an authentic discernment
because while
AI systems can be tremendously
illuminating, can be informative, can
summarize large bodies of data that
would take us many hours, days, years
sometimes to reflect upon. They can
never replace the very human
decision-making process and that moral
responsibility because ultimately we're
going to be responsible as human agents
for decisions that are made in our
personal life but also decisions that
are made in the criminal justice system
for instance. So these design issues
have uh very widpread
uh societal impact as well and we don't
want to outsource what is most human. We
want to enhance our capacities to
understand situations to assess them
better and to make responsible
decisions.
>> And father, you mentioned, you know,
kind of that that moral worth that that
humans have and that ability for us to
make moral judgments. There was a recent
um I think it was a research paper that
was provided by anthropic where they
talked about the moral status of um of
these AI systems and the potential,
>> you know, as things continue to
progress, what do we do with that? What
what does the church make of th of those
claims?
Well, there is something very unique
about the the human being. We see the
human being as having these capacities
for intellectual insight, these
capacities for free decisions. And so
these AI systems might be able to
emulate and mimic some of the
expressions of those human
characteristics, but we don't want to
blur the lines here. We want to keep in
mind the clear differences between human
beings and the different products
artifacts that they design. We want to
make sure that there these AI systems
remain as tools, tools to improve, to
illumin to aid and assist those unique
human characteristics, those unique
capacities. What we don't want to do is
try to imagine uh some sort of new
superior
digital person, if you will. And we
don't want to confuse the what is
mimicked and systems that emulate these
characteristics with actual persons. So
I would be very uncomfortable to start
attributing a kind of moral status to
the actual systems. I'm certainly
concerned about the moral implications
of the human decisions that are made in
design and development of the systems,
but I I wouldn't want to absolve the
human beings of their responsibility for
the decisions that are made. And I want
to keep that distinction between the
human and the machine quite clear as we
go along. And that makes me think,
father, of um of I know one of the
topics that's dear to your heart, which
is um looking at that that kind of that
blurring within like artificial intimacy
and and how these systems will take up
more and more space in in you know
people's lives as as loneliness as um
>> as technology kind of moves into these
spaces and and takes up more and more of
our time.
>> Sure. Because as the systems get better
and better about guiding us or
suggesting information, the temptation
sets in to think of them as more
reliable, more available, more
supportive of us than real life human
beings. But one of the beauties about
human interpersonal relationships is
that good friends, good family members
sometimes challenge us, sometimes
correct us, and they also can exercise
an empathy that these uh systems will
always lack. So there's always going to
be uh a kind of asymmetry between humans
and the machines that they use. like
we'll we'll be able to uh find a lot of
benefit even guidance from them, but
there's not that same interpersonal
exchange of love, of care, of sympathy
and compassion, right? Because they
can't really empathize with us without
an emotional life. They can't suffer
with us. They can't have that true
authentic compassion. So, as helpful as
they may be as tools, they're not going
to or ought not to replace these other
really enriching relationships in our
lives, which again can be uncomfortable,
can be very hard to develop, can be hard
to sustain,
>> but are some of the richest experiences
of our life. Now, I'm very open to the
possibility that some of the AI systems
can provide some aid, especially people
who struggle for a particular reason.
Maybe because of trauma, maybe because
because they're neurologically divergent
or they're going through a difficult
time or they're in a new social
situation. I'm open to getting some
initial training in the social life
through these systems, a kind of social
simulator. But I think that that social
simulation ought always to be geared to
a better and richer real life, realworld
interpersonal experience with other
human beings. So if we have that goal in
mind, then they can assist along the
way, but they should aid, not replace.
And father, I want to I want to touch
back on something that you you'd
mentioned about um kind of that blurring
of the line with uh with AI and with
these technologies. Something that I
find kind of worrisome. I mean there
there is an aspect where I I am inspired
because I think that innovation is a
beautiful thing and I think that
innovation kind of that that mission of
of of the individual to be led by their
curiosity to continue to develop to to
make their circumstances better. I think
that's incredible and I'm a huge you
know believer in curiosity and
creativity. Something that I find
uniquely challenging and worrisome
though about the AI space in particular
is that that technology,
not only is it kind of developing at a
speed that for the average person is
almost impossible to keep up with, but
another thing is that it it it allows
for people's weaknesses and negative
characteristics and qualities to be
exaggerated to such a proportion that I
feel like, okay, I'm I'm in I'm an
adult. I have children. I have a lot of
things that keep me in the real world.
But if someone has not built in the
habits to really learn and spend time
learning or has not developed the
courage or that personal will to you
know live in the real world and to meet
someone and to you know pursue that
person and to to to develop themselves
in a way where you're attractive to
other people and you bring good people
together. Um AI seems to be accelerating
that. And one of the uh subjects that I
know that you're passionate about and
you're studying actively is that area of
artificial intimacy, that area of
artificial companionship. Um and this is
all stuff that seemed just a few years
ago to be something that was relatively
science fictionesque.
>> Sure.
>> How is the church um encouraging young
people to, you know, actually live in
the real world and pursue relationships
that are meaningful and can be
challenging and can be hurtful and all
those things, but that within that pain
we grow. How is the church um engaging
in that space and you know not just with
artificial intimacy but also within that
whole gamified universe where people can
find real meaning real value real
development but it's all visual and I'm
not saying there's not I'm not saying
that there's not value in team building
those team qualities and getting better
at something but if you're just
amilarating a digital circumstances
that's providing you
>> um satisfaction but is not actually
making you heroic in that realense How
how do you think about that and how do
you how are you actively engaging to to
to bring the church's message into that
space?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. As a
Catholic educator, as a professor, I'm
constantly thinking about how I can help
my students form the human, emotional,
and social skills that the church has
always promoted, but that in a sense are
more valuable than ever because so much
is being automated and so much more will
be automated. So if my focus is
primarily on distributing a set of
information, then I'm failing them
because they can thankfully get a lot of
that information already and it will
only be more accessible to them in the
future, which is generally a good thing.
But that increase in information is no
guarantee for an increase in
discernment, an increase in prudence, or
an increase in wisdom. So I need to help
them form those skills which are going
to come through lots of different paths
right dialogue
>> confrontation with different views.
>> I think the church has been very good in
her history in helping to develop the
university system in the scholastic
debates that people like Thomas Aquinus
had.
>> That's such an amazing structure for us
today where you go and you listen and
study attentively all the different
worldviews that are out there. all the
philosophies, all the religions, and you
search out any elements of truth that
can be found there, and you see how you
can bring those elements together into a
unified worldview, into a unified
picture. And you do that sometimes in a
clash of views with debate, that's
respectful, but that's serious. So, I
really enjoy bringing my students into
those conversations to have a a
sympathetic look at worldviews that are
not their own
>> and then have them enter into formal
debate or critical conversations where
they're able to explore the nuances on
perspectives and where they're able to
really assimilate more deeply their own
convictions and see how those beautiful
ideas actually impact their life. Right?
because their time of formal education
will end, but the different habits, the
virtues that they form, intellectual
virtues, moral virtues, that's what's
really going to drive them forward in
the future. So, I think the church is
really well equipped with her patrimony
of wisdom and her long-standing
commitment to education. So, we should
really be on the forefront of this. We
should be continue to be leaders in this
area to make sure that we're we're
forming those virtues that are
transferable, right? They're not going
to go out of date. They don't have an
expiration date just because of a new
technological development. They're
they're actually something they can
bring with them to different social
settings, to new situations. And so
that's one area where I think the the
church can do a lot that educational
system. And of course, the
responsibility of education also falls
to to parents to be able to assist their
their children and to help families
develop in that little school of virtue,
the domestic church, where you're
constantly, and you know full well as a
father, as a husband, you're called day
in and day out to new forms of
self-sacrifice you probably didn't even
know existed.
>> There's no off switch.
>> No, no, no. And father, as um as AI
continues to progress, um we know from
from our listeners, from our
conversations, from from people, you
know, that we've just in daily contact
with that there there is some anxiety.
There's um stress about what what's work
going to look like? What's society going
to look like? What, you know, what are
the economics and political
circumstances? How are they going to be
transformed by this technology? if you
um can you help our audience paint a
picture of what does a good future look
like where AI is, you know, is
developed, is mature, is being used in
all the ways that we hope it it can be
used for and um and how do we get there?
[laughter]
>> I bet every world leader would like to
know this this uh answer, right?
>> Well, I think that we can take the right
steps if we're developing those virtues
that I alluded to earlier. If we help
people recognize the value of work as a
path of human growth, as a path of
collaboration,
>> no matter how small it that work may
seem or how
big it may be on the on the world stage,
there's a sense that there there should
be an intrinsic goodness, a formative
value to your work that it's it's a
place where you're using your unique
talent
>> at the service of others. I was reading
an author recently who's heavily
involved in a business school and he
said human excellence is often achieved
when we take our competency and we put
it at the service of others. So I think
that's what we want to look for. Whether
you're doing coding, whether you're
painting buildings, whether you're
designing cars, whether you're writing
books, you want to take your gifts and
achieve a competency in that field
>> and put that competency at the service
of others that that interpersonal
exchange or really recognize our need
for one another. I think if we can
achieve that exchange and we find value
in the work whatever it may be then we
can go forward with a sense of meaning
and purpose.
>> Yeah. But father, if I can just push
back for one second, um like I I I 100%
agree with that. But um there have been,
you know, people within, you know, in
very high places, you know, in the
political and economic sphere that where
they're talking about, you know, and I I
don't know, obviously no one knows how
soon this will happen, but they're
talking about like 40% unemployment by
2030, whether it's because of
transportation, whether it's because of
automation, whether it's, you know,
white collar, blue collar. And um I I
100% agree that that um work is meaning,
work is dignity, work is is is beyond
just the economic, you know, value and
how much you're contributing in that
sense. But when we're in a place which
seems at least not too far away, where
>> there's a huge percentage of that
population that actually cannot add any
positive economic value, they are they
are not able to. And
>> that's a very scary place. And if we
don't get that right, and I believe and
we all believe here that um if the
church is not at the at the center of
that, um you know, people can be very
angry, people can be very desperate, and
that can be a very dark and scary place,
right?
>> How
h how do we get past that or how do we
at least paint a picture and and and
arrive at a place where,
>> you know, where it's okay?
>> Yeah, that's that's a challenging
question. I was thinking of the fact
that the new pope chose the name Leo the
14th and of course he is evoking his
predecessor Leo I 13th and one of Leo I
13th's major contributions was
developing this contemporary notion of
Catholic social teaching
>> and Leo saw the new things the new
things were heavily tied to
technological developments and the human
implications of those technological
developments and he placed the attention
of the church squarely on worker
dignity.
worker rights and finding the best ways
to organize them so that those who
weren't really appearing to contribute
much to society were not just set aside
and thrown aside as useless. So I think
that one of the many challenges of this
pontificate together with all of his
adviserss and and everyone else who has
insights on this issue is to really
develop a kind of new deepened
appreciation for the dignity of each
human person and create the proper
social structures so that those who are
not able to pivot quickly in this huge
economic disruption
>> are not just forgotten and left behind.
that there's some sort of safety net
there and assistance and education so
that they can transition to a way of
actually using their time and talents in
a valuable worthwhile way and and not
forgotten and set aside. But that's
going to be a major major uh challenge
and commitment on the part of the church
and collaboration with all the other
people in the world who are thinking
seriously about this. And then father, I
guess my my final question would be
where do you think we're going to be in
a few in a few years with Catholic AI?
What what are your hopes with Catholic
AI?
>> Well, I want to see Catholic AI as a
reality that is readily acknowledged and
accessible not only to Catholics but to
those outside the church. So I want
reliable responses to those questions of
mere [clears throat] curiosity. We just
live through a conclave where the entire
world is spending hours each day waiting
for white smoke to come out of a
chimney. There's clearly this curiosity,
this interest that people have in the
institution of the church. And so I want
all of those people in those moments of
grace where they might just have an
interesting question about the church to
have ready access to reliable
information that they can then reflect
upon and bring up with real life
Catholics and practicing Catholics. But
I think that Catholic AI should be an
easy entry point for people who have
those questions, concerns, confusions,
maybe even objections uh to the faith.
And so I want to see this as being
something that's widespread, readily
accessible. And then I also want to see
Catholic values instilled in how we use
AI and all those other fields we
mentioned earlier, right? So that the
health care system is taking advantage
of developments in drug discovery, in
drug testing and drug development. We're
making breakthroughs, for instance, in
the treatment of Alzheimer's, in in
dementia. we're really putting these
tools at the service of the weak, the
frail, the vulnerable, the forgotten. Uh
I want to see that becoming more
widespread. And I want us to kind of
shift away from just thinking of these
as nice, interesting, sometimes scary
tools of a few people who happen to be
technologically inclined to just really
being inbuilt, integrated into what we
consider most important in life.
>> Yeah. And father, I think my my personal
opinion is that as the values that are
building the majority of these AI
systems and we've we've talked a lot off
air about transhumanism and about these
different value systems that aren't
grounded in something that is really
truly faithful. I think that Catholic AI
is going to take a larger and larger
space because people are going to want
to have, you know, something that's
that's that's documented, that's
doctrinal, that has that authority and
that clarity that the church can
provide. Why do you think um what do you
think are the biggest challenges for us
to get there though where where more
people start to want to be participating
in Catholic AI?
>> Well, there can be a fear that Catholic
AI is something that's sectarian. It's
just one particular group and there are
lots of value systems and lots of
different perspectives on how to
organize your life. So why pay attention
to Catholicism as opposed to to other
systems? And so I get that that's the
perennial challenge of pluralism, right?
And I think that's going to be with us
for a while. One of the things that I
think is very exciting about Catholic AI
in that regard is that people are
starting to discover how rich and
nuanced the Catholic tradition is. And
they're starting to discover that these
aren't just a set of fairy tale ideas
that have been imposed from one
generation to another. That there's
actually a lot of serious thought,
reflection, and debate. So people are
starting to find out about Thomas
Aquinas, about St. Augustine. They say,
"Well, wait a second. these really
brilliant people actually wrestled with
the kind of issues that I have today and
this Catholic system is not so narrow or
close to other elements. So I think that
this is actually a key moment for us to
expose more people to that richness and
that nuance and give them that space to
wrestle with the deep questions to to
prompt to go deeper to find better
arguments, better resources. And we
ought to have a healthy confidence that
this is not just a narrowminded
sectarian system and not just one among
many, but that there's space to
integrate whatever is true, good, and
beautiful in all these different
philosophies or or ways of thinking into
kind of a coherent hole. And I think
that that's an attractive selling point
to Catholicism in general, but Catholic
AI in particular, because we feel the
weight of fragmentation. I can look up
anything, anytime, any place. I have
information with me everywhere. But how
does that all fit together? How how do I
bring these truths together? And how do
those truths actually speak to my life?
Like, how what do they have to say about
how I raise my children? What do they
say about how I treat other people at
work? Catholicism gives people the
possibility of doing that. And I think
that that's an exciting opportunity for
Catholic AI to engage with those
questions and let people have fun, let
people challenge the system, let people
uh ask and kind of enter into this
updated version of the Scholastic
University where you'd have the disputed
questions where you'd have the back and
forth. uh it's the opportunity to kind
of bring that reality and that
harmonization of different disciplines
that existed in the great universities
of the past. Maybe we can bring that
reality to every phone, every computer
in the world. And that's exciting.
>> And father, that's I mean that's so
exciting that you know AI and
particularly Catholic AI can can provide
that nuance, can provide that
information, that context, that history.
Those are things that um that I actually
actively use every day on Magisterium
AI. But father, what are the um what are
the specific areas where AI should not
go and cannot go?
>> Well, we talked a lot about that
intimacy, right? So there is no AI
system that can replace human friendship
and there's no AI system that's going to
be able to take away the value for
instance of a good spiritual director
because a good spiritual director
doesn't just give you information. The
good spiritual director accompanies you
on this journey of growth. And so some
applications can give you sound advice,
but you need that living person, that
guide to really show you how to apply
that more concretely to your state, to
your challenges, to your reality. So I
would never want to lose that unique
role of authentic companionship and
friendship, that unique role of
spiritual director. And then we get to,
of course, the sacraments, which I think
about often as a priest, right? I I have
full job security in that sense because
no AI system is ever going to be able to
administer the sacraments. This speaks
to the incarnational logic of the
church, right? We believe in a God who
became man who took on human flesh and
who interacts with fleshy beings, human
beings through visible signs. And so he
continues his ministry in a very
physical, grounded, rooted and communal
reality of the church. So no matter how
many brilliant insights you're able to
find in AI systems, thanks be to God,
there's no replacing the sacramental
system, that lived here and now
experience of the divine, of the
eternal. And it's not just a private me
and Jesus experience. It's always a
communal experience. We're baptized,
surrounded by our loved ones. We're
married in the in the presence of a
community, right? We celebrate the
eukarist together as a people of God on
a journey, on a pilgrimage toward heaven
together. So, in a world where we can
often feel isolated and even absorbed by
really attractive digital devices, the
church says, "Wait, there's more.
There's the embodied experience and
there's the communal experience. And I
think that what things like magisterium
AI do so well is there the window, the
opening to the curious or to those who
just want to go deeper. And then from
there, you're directed into that
communal experience. You're directed
into a church community. You're directed
into a one-on-one conversation with a
trusted spiritual guide. So, I think
there there should be that
collaboration. It's not always easy to
see how to best make that transition.
So, that's something I think we're
continuing to think a lot about, but
that's definitely the goal. This this
may be the starting point for some
growth, but you're really going to
flourish in the community with other
believers.
>> Yeah. And father, what do you say to
someone who's like, "Well, I live in a
very isolated region. There are no
priests or there's very few priests. Um,
there's, you know, this robot priest
that comes in and by the way, he's more
accurate. he gets his theology 100% I
feel comfortable because of of whatever.
Um how how do we push back on that where
you know there's also the temptation I
remember during COVID where I want to
live stream mass I'm you know I don't
want to get up and go to to mass because
it's too far or it's complicated or you
know feels like technology can also in
in many respects get in the way in that
sense.
>> Yeah. So let's leverage the benefits
there. Let's gain all of the great
insight from a well-trained system and
and the information, but there's
something indispensable and unique about
that embodied experience, the communal
experience. As I said, in the
sacramental system, it's God himself and
his church has willed to transmit
invisible grace through visible forms.
So, I think we can be very confident
that we're gaining and we're growing in
something in a very unique way. So
that's at the highest supernatural
level, right? In the level of faith that
God has chosen to transmit these
invisible graces to us in a concrete
visible manner in a sacramental system.
But I think if we trust in those
spiritual benefits along the way, we get
a lot of just basic human benefits. we
start to see that as great and reliable
as that robot is
is lacking that empathy, that sympathy,
that compassion, that real care and
concern that I can find in the weak, in
the frail and the limited brother and
sister that I encounter when I go to
receive that spiritual grace. So I think
sometimes when we pursue that unique
encounter with God along the way our
human interactions are actually enriched
and we're going to see their faults and
failings. But there's something
beautiful about knowing that they bear
with our faults and failings. They
support us in our faults and failings
because of a real concern and care for
us and not simply because they're
programmed to give a certain response
that flatters us or builds us up or
makes or taps into our psychological
vulnerabilities.
>> Beautiful. Well, Father, thank you so
much. I could spend an eternity uh
speaking with you. And to all of you who
might have questions, who want to go
deeper into your faith or your
understanding the history of the church
or getting context or even you know the
readings of the day, uh we invite you
all to use Magisterium AI, the number
one Catholic answer engine in the world.
And that's it for the Catholic futurist.
My name is Benjamin Crockett and I'll
see you